<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Psychoros</title>
  <subtitle>The dancing ground of the soul</subtitle>
  <link href="https://www.psychoros.com/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://www.psychoros.com/" />
  <updated>1950-03-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://www.psychoros.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Loren Amelang</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Infection</title>
    <link href="https://www.psychoros.com/blog/infection/" />
    <updated>1950-03-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.psychoros.com/blog/infection/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;  &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://www.psychoros.com/.11ty/image/?src=content%2Fblog%2Finfection%2Fbacteria-border-770-35.jpg&amp;width=770&amp;format=avif&amp;via=transform 770w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://www.psychoros.com/.11ty/image/?src=content%2Fblog%2Finfection%2Fbacteria-border-770-35.jpg&amp;width=770&amp;format=webp&amp;via=transform 770w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://www.psychoros.com/.11ty/image/?src=content%2Fblog%2Finfection%2Fbacteria-border-770-35.jpg&amp;width=770&amp;format=jpeg&amp;via=transform&quot; alt=&quot;Long narrow stripe of colorful cartoon germs.&quot; width=&quot;770&quot; height=&quot;35&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infections came up often. I have records of three positive chest X-rays for TB before I was three. I was tested for brucellosis (bovine tuberculosis), apparently positive since I was then X-rayed again for that. Of the antibiotics, only the sulfonamides were common then. I&#39;d received &amp;quot;sulfa&amp;quot; when my mother&#39;s TB was discovered, but it was reportedly ineffective against TB or brucellosis, so maybe they suspected something else on top of those. A 1937 paper describes treating brucellosis with IV mercurochrome, or with fever induced by brucellin &amp;quot;vaccine&amp;quot;, as more effective, but I definitely did not undergo that. Penicillin arrived about the same time I did, but there is no record of my ever receiving any.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t consciously remember, but I&#39;d be quite surprised if I was not exposed to infected milk and meat on my grandfather&#39;s farm, as well as airborne infection. My grandfather and mother both had pulmonary #Tuberculosis. My skin tests have always been positive - but the skin test responds to both &amp;quot;human&amp;quot; and bovine tuberculosis, so that proves nothing about whether my tonsil and gland infections were tubercular. I&#39;ve never been diagnosed with active pulmonary TB, though doctors argued back and forth about it for my first year of college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just learned about Tuberculous Cervical Adenitis from a 1923 paper. Tuberculosis from infected milk enters the body through the tonsils and adenoids, and spreads to all the nearby glands in the neck. A healthy body can fight this off, but a reservoir of infection like a rotten tooth can provide more threat than the immune system can handle. Once the deeper glands are tuberculous, their boundaries are poorly defined. And &amp;quot;There is no satisfactory landmark or method of identifying the [ spinal #AccessoryNerve ] with certainty.&amp;quot; (That will become a critical factor when they remove my #Tonsils !)
  &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;STONE, J. S. (1923). Tuberculous Cervical Adenitis in Children. The Boston Medical and Surgical Journal, 188(9), 272-275. doi:10.1056/nejm192303011880907 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sci-hub.se/10.1056/NEJM192303011880907#&quot;&gt;https://sci-hub.se/10.1056/NEJM192303011880907#&lt;/a&gt;  (Page 274, right column)
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My primitive family #Dentist believed filling cavities in &amp;quot;baby&amp;quot; teeth was unnecessary, and encouraged my parents to simply allow them to rot away on their own. I spent years of my childhood with deep cavities in the center of each of my solidly anchored original molars, a disgusting taste and smell, and undoubtedly the reservoir of infection that kept my tonsils and glands swollen. It was so bad I kept a bent paper clip in my pocket at all times, and would use it not only to dislodge trapped food, but to dig the painfully exposed parts of the nerves out of the roots of the hollowed out teeth. Better a few moments of blinding intentional pain than not being able to chew at all...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;History of antibiotics:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reactgroup.org/toolbox/understand/antibiotics/development-of-antibiotics-as-medicines/&quot;&gt;https://www.reactgroup.org/toolbox/understand/antibiotics/development-of-antibiotics-as-medicines/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pre-antibiotic treatment for brucellosis or &amp;quot;undulant fever&amp;quot;: &lt;br&gt;
ERVIN, C. E. (1937). THE DIAGNOSIS AND TREATMENT OF UNDULANT FEVER. Journal of the American Medical Association, 109(24), 1966. doi:10.1001/jama.1937.02780500022008
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sci-hub.se/10.1001/jama.1937.02780500022008&quot;&gt;https://sci-hub.se/10.1001/jama.1937.02780500022008&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Sci-Hub may show a word Captcha with only Russian cues - just type the letters and press Enter.)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My Origin 🎉</title>
    <link href="https://www.psychoros.com/blog/my-origin/" />
    <updated>1947-05-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.psychoros.com/blog/my-origin/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;  &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://www.psychoros.com/.11ty/image/?src=content%2Fblog%2Fmy-origin%2FdnaComp-770-35.jpeg&amp;width=770&amp;format=avif&amp;via=transform 770w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://www.psychoros.com/.11ty/image/?src=content%2Fblog%2Fmy-origin%2FdnaComp-770-35.jpeg&amp;width=770&amp;format=webp&amp;via=transform 770w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://www.psychoros.com/.11ty/image/?src=content%2Fblog%2Fmy-origin%2FdnaComp-770-35.jpeg&amp;width=770&amp;format=jpeg&amp;via=transform&quot; alt=&quot;Long narrow stripe of colorful spiraling DNA.&quot; width=&quot;770&quot; height=&quot;35&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mother built bombers during WWII. My dad flew as a radio operator in the Pacific war. They returned to hide in their tiny Midwestern town and have a family. Yes, I&#39;m a &amp;quot;boomer&amp;quot;. Dad signed on at the local cement plant as an hourly worker, while mom minded the house and said the &amp;quot;happiest time of her life was working in the bomber plant.&amp;quot; Their idyll was short lived - when I was two years and nine months old mom was overcome by the tuberculosis we both caught from her father, and she nearly died in the state hospital. But she came back after twenty months and lived a long life. She built most of the 50+ feet of concrete and stone wall along the driveway, ruled family finances with an iron fist, and corrected my father and me at the first hint of chauvinism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The balance to my controlling feminist mother was provided by the aunt and uncle I lived with while she was in the TB hospital, and the family farm they ran together. Without that perspective I&#39;d probably be a raging fascist instead of eternally curious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My aunt tended the garden, canned dozens of jars of vegetables for winter, maintained the cream separator and made butter, cared for and processed the chickens, and occasionally taught one-room country school. My uncle drove tractors, baled hay, welded broken equipment, tended the cattle and hogs, dealt with the ax and chopping block when it was time to process chickens, and taught me by example the curiosity and patience to deal with nature and technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sounds horribly gendered, but compared to my life in town it was blessed freedom. There were no arbitrary rules, no negative judgments. If you knew how to do something you were free to put on the appropriate clothes for the task and go do it. What gender you felt or were supposed to feel just never came up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back with my parents, I felt less secure. I was a &amp;quot;sensitive&amp;quot; kid, not in today&#39;s sense of tantrums and meltdowns, emotional overload, but in noticing subtle details of adult life and thinking deeply about their meanings. The &amp;quot;fly story&amp;quot; was my parents&#39; favorite, though they completely misinterpreted my reaction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d followed my dad to the bathroom to check the indoor-outdoor thermometer beside the window, because if it wasn&#39;t above 70 degrees I was not allowed to go outside. (Of course when school started I had to walk there no matter how far below zero it was...) Dad swatted a fly on the window with his bare hand, picked it up, tossed it in the open toilet, and immediately flushed. It was not the killing that bothered me, I saw animals killed all the time. It was being treated like shit, flushed and forgotten, irretrievably extinguished in an instant with no apparent concern at all. I felt extremely vulnerable and cried inconsolably. Who was this man I was now bound to? Could I be zapped away as suddenly and totally?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>